<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Owburne in Buckinghamshire at the funerall of the right worshipfull, and truly religious gentlewoman, Mris Margaret Elmes On the twenty-seaventh of Iuly. 1641. By George Burches batchlour of divinity.</title>
            <author>Burches, George, d. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31470</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30217)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31470)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1863:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Owburne in Buckinghamshire at the funerall of the right worshipfull, and truly religious gentlewoman, Mris Margaret Elmes On the twenty-seaventh of Iuly. 1641. By George Burches batchlour of divinity.</title>
                  <author>Burches, George, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Leon. Lichfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elmes, Margaret, d. 1641.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31470:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at OWBVRNE IN <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CKINGHAMSHIRE</hi> AT The Funerall of the Right Worſhipfull, and truly Religious Gentlewoman, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> MARGARET ELMES. On the twenty-ſeaventh of <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>By GEORGE BURCHES Batchlour of <hi>Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 2.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Be thou faithfull unto death, and I will give thee a Crowne of Life.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by LEON. LICHFIELD, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31470:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31470:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE <hi>AND</hi> TRVLY VERTVOVS M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> IANE GOODWIN Wife to the Right Worſhipfull ARTHUR GOODWIN <hi>Eſq.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Miſtris,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> KNOW it is an unwelcome meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to be the Herauld of ill newes. Such tidings are like the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites</hi> to <hi>David;</hi> or <hi>Jonah's</hi> Sermon to the <hi>Ninivites</hi> adminiſtring nothing but
<pb facs="tcp:31470:3"/>ſorrow. But when withall I apprehend your goodneſſe and wiſdome, how it can make the best uſe of the loſſe of your neareſt friends, J am the more emboldened to preſent theſe unwelcome and unworthy lines to your kind acceptance. It is an unalterable law like that of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serius aut si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tam properamus ad unam.</note> 
               <hi>ſooner or later we all haſten to the ſame end.</hi> Mans dayes are numbred, his period of time appointed, and his bound he cannot paſse. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> muſt part, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Rachell</hi> muſt be ſeparated, and though <hi>Ruth</hi> and <hi>Naomi</hi> be never ſo endeered friends, yet death will divide them. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory of man as the flower of the field. The graſſe withereth, the flower fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,</hi> and ſo muſt the rareſt pieces of nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to duſt. It's true, you have loſt a moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſiſter in law, the Church a gracious Saint, the poore a deare friend: yet muſt all reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented ſeeing it is by the determinate hand of God. It had been a great happineſse that ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a ſtarre might have longer ſhined (if God had ſo pleaſed) in the Orbe where once ſhee gave ſuch a comely lustre. But ſeeing now we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived
<pb facs="tcp:31470:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:31470:4"/>of her light, I meane that comfort and ſweet ſociety which was enjoyed in her preſence, we muſt reſt contented, and labour to ſee the hand of God in it; whoſe will is the rule of his actions, and is therefore pleaſed to adde one member unto the head to live for ever with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. As thoſe that would inhabit the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> were to wade through the banks and ſtreames of the river <hi>Jordan</hi> with <hi>Joſuah.</hi> So they that will arive at that <hi>Canaan</hi> which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove muſt wade firſt through the river <hi>Lethe</hi> here with their guide and forerunner <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Let it therefore comfort you that ſhe is with her Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and now nothing remaines but her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues as lively monuments of her eternall worth. In which Catalogue J will mention but one,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Humilitas virtus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum</hi> 1a, 2a, 3a. <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> which was her <hi>Humility,</hi> rarely to be found in perſons of her ranck. Her goodneſſe having learned that this grace is the firſt, ſecond, and third ſtayre of true Christian nobility. By this ſhe hath now aſcended to happineſſe. For the high and lofty one (as the Prophet ſpeakes,) that inhabiteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, delighting to reſide in an humble ſoule, hath eternized her worth; and therefore would
<pb facs="tcp:31470:5"/>ſuffer her no longer to dwell in ſo unworthy a countrey, but thinking her more fit for a greater honour, and a better place hath crowned her in his owne kingdome. May it pleaſe you therefore to give leave to publiſh to the world under the Convoy of your worthy name, this meane, but faithfull testimony of my dutifull affection and unfeigned eſtimation of thoſe ſaving graces, which (J am perſwaded) were lodged in her noble Brest. This is the firſt time that ever I ſet to ſea in this publick manner, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my name came into the <hi>Printers ſtocks.</hi> And had it not been out of conſcience of my thankfullneſſe to my bleſsed friend of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deare memory, rather to enliven her worth then to ſpread my owne. J would still have kept my owne private way, and never have rode in the common dust. But ſo abounding was her goodneſſe, that I could not reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to bury her fame in my owne breſt, but muſt endeavour to erect a monument of her in paper to all the world. And firſt to you most vertuous <hi>M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>,</hi> whom I humbly crave to lodge theſe pocre endeavours in your good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb facs="tcp:31470:3"/>and the rather for her ſake whoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe yet ſparkles in your eyes. And the Image of whoſe vertues is in this little Codicill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to you; ſo ſhall you oblige me who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant GEOR. BURCHES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31470:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. TIM. 4.7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>7.</hi> J have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>8.</hi> Henceforth there is laid up for me a crowne of righteouſneſse.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O omit the context which is obvious to them that will but read the precedent verſes. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is comprized and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to our conſideration, the happy conſequence and good ſucceſſe which will follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the painefull endeavours the faithful undergoe in their ſpiritual warfare. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in contending for earthly things, it oftentimes falls out that ſome beat the buſh and others catch the Birds, ſome break the bone and others eat the marrow: in a word ſome take the paines and others
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31470:6"/>attaine the prize. Yet in the chriſtian combat and ſpirituall conflict betwixt the ſonnes and ſervants of God it is not ſo; for be they endurers of the ſweat they ſhall be enjoyers of the ſweet; God out of his mercy hath promiſed, and out of his truth will ſee performed, that they ſhall be ſure to enjoy an ample and glorious reward. For when the thread of their dayes is ſpunne, and their ſoules brought to a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cataſtrophe, then ſhall they inherit what here is promiſed <hi>a Crowne of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Which makes them with <hi>S. Paul</hi> to conclude with this heavenly expreſſion, <hi>I have fought &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which text I find expreſt by two ſeverall Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors.</p>
            <p>The former drawne from Fighters, the latter from Runners.</p>
            <p>In the former is implyed,
<list>
                  <item>1. The ſouldiers who are to fight, the faithfull, intimated in the expreſſion of <hi>S. Paul, J have fought.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Their weapons, which though all be not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed yet is the chief one mentioned, which is the ſhield of faith, <hi>I have kept the faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Their valour, they are not faint-hearted but ſtand to their colours till they finiſh their courſe.</item>
                  <item>4. The prize which they obtaine by fighting, and that is no leſſe then <hi>a Crowne of righteouſneſse.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the latter is ſet forth,
<list>
                  <item>1. the runners, intimated in this particle I, the faithfull.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31470:6"/>
                  <item>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Their race, which is the true profeſſion of the faith.</item>
                  <item>3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Their round or continuance of it, they are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fainting nor breathles, but goe on ſtoutly till they have finiſhed their courſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the reward they obtaine by running, which is encouragement enough for their conſtancy, <hi>a Crowne of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which particulars let us ſumme up into three maine concluſions worthy our beſt conſideration.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Faithfull men are military men.</item>
               <item>2. As they are military ſo they are mortall.</item>
               <item>3. If they fight couragiouſly their endeavours ſhall not be fruſtrated but amply rewarded, they ſhall receive <hi>a Crowne of righteouſneſse.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To begin with the firſt, faithfull men are military men. Thus did the wreſtling of <hi>Iſrael</hi> prefigure, which makes <hi>S. Paul</hi> oft-times to give it in charge to <hi>stand faſt</hi> like valiant ſouldiers,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.13.</note> and <hi>quit our ſelves like men and be ſtrong.</hi> As the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> fought many a dreadfull battaile and encountred with the great <hi>Anakims</hi> before they could ſet foot in <hi>Canaan.</hi> So thoſe which are the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God are ſtill up in armes, and in danger of many a dreadfull and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full skirmiſh, whiles they are marching forwards towards that <hi>Canaan</hi> which is above. Hence not unfitly that ſaying of holy <hi>Iob</hi> may bee applyed in this place: The life of man is a warfare upon earth. Put the caſe there were a man that had ſome great reward propoſed unto him, but with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31470:7"/>That firſt he muſt ſubdue ſome tyrants, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw ſome monſter, or vanquiſh ſome huge and hideous Gyant. As we read of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> and as the Poets doe relate of <hi>Hercules,</hi> could not theſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be attained unto, then by ſome conflict or bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy combat. <hi>Mutato nomine de te fabula narratur.</hi> Change but the name, this is true of every faithfull chriſtian. God in heaven hath propoſed a reward to him though reſident upon earth, in attaining where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hee hath moſt puiſſant and powerfull enemies to encounter with, moſt direfull and dreadfull mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which are up in armes and daily adde battaile to him. So tyrannicall are they, that without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion they labour to captivate him, and bring him from bleſſed freedom to ſlaviſh &amp; helliſh thraldom. The champions in which combat we meet with, are chiefly theſe three. The <hi>fleſh,</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>devill,</hi> which have entred into league and joyned their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together that like a threefold cord they cannot eaſily be broken. The <hi>fleſh</hi> like an inbred and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickenimy is alwaies ſwelling, and rebellious againſt the ſpirit; ſtriving and ſtrugling for ſoveraignty and ſuperiority. This great <hi>Goliah</hi> doth ſtill bid battaile to little <hi>David.</hi> Alwayes fighting againſt the ſpirit, and never fayling to oppoſe it as appeares by the words of <hi>S.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>Paul. Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>The fleſh luſteth against the ſpirit and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and theſe are contrary the one to the other.</hi> the truth hereof the Apoſtle finding dayly by experience in himſelfe breakes forth into this patheticall Epiphonema. <hi>O
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31470:7"/>wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death.</hi> In ſubdueing whereof there is ſo much the harder fight, by how much the more danger it is to encounter with a familiar, then an open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. The <hi>world</hi> doth challenge a chriſtian into the open field, ſometime by violence as by croſſes and perſecution, by open actions and evill ſpeeches: and ſometimes by deceitfull pollicies, <hi>Iudas like</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding kiſſes when ſhe propounds deſtruction; under her alluring pleaſures ſhe ſhrowdes her deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Like another <hi>Eve</hi> alwaies egging, like another <hi>Dalilah</hi> alwayes tempting, and by her Syrene ſweet notes of profits, and of pleaſures, labours to drown the ſoule in the full ſea of perdition. The <hi>devill</hi> is no leſſe ready to aſſay and aſſault him;
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>For he goes about</hi> (as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>like a roaring Lyon ſeking whom he may devoure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4.13.</note> Who as he would not ſuffer our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to bee at reſt, but did ſet upon him the 1, 2, and 3. time. No more will hee permit thoſe, who are members of that body whereof Chriſt is the head, who are branches of that vine whereof Chriſt is the root, who are ſheep of that ſheepfold whereof Chriſt is the ſheapheard; in a word, who are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that kingdome whereof Chriſt Ieſus is the king to be in quiet; but rather then hee ſhall bee free from encounters; <hi>Proteus-like,</hi> he will by changing himſelfe into many ſhapes, and turning himſelfe into an Angell of light, give them cauſe continually to looke and to lay about them. As Chriſt was, ſo muſt we be in this world. No ſooner was he conſecrated
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31470:8"/>by his ſolemne Baptiſme to the work of a Mediator, but preſently was aſſaulted by the tempter. And no ſooner doth any one give up his name to Chriſt and breake forth out of that helliſh power under which He was kept; but forthwith <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his hoſts, Satan and his confederates purſue him with deadly fury, and powre forth floods of malice and rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.
<note place="margin">Nunquam bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la boni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam diſſidia ceſſant. Et quae cum cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet mens pia ſemper habet. Proſper.</note> Hell and death are at truce with wicked men; there is a covenant and an agreement betwixt them, Satan holds his poſſeſſion in peace; but when a ſtronger then hee commeth and overcommeth: from that time there is implacable venome and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility againſt ſuch a ſoule. The power and policy of that grand enemy the divell, the luſts and vanity, the frownes and flattery of this ſinfull world: in a word, the affections, inclinations, and deceits of our fleſhly hearts, will ever ply the ſoule of a chriſtian and force it to perpetuall combats. It was not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without good cauſe that S.
<note place="margin">Eph. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Paul Epheſ.</hi> 6.10. did <hi>claſsicum canere</hi> ſtrike up an Alarm unto his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, wiſhing the <hi>Epheſians</hi> and in them all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to <hi>bee ſtrong in the Lord and in the power of his might, to put on the whole armour of God,</hi> to gird our loynes with verity, to have on the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, to be ſhodde with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace, to take up the ſhield of faith the helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword of the ſpirit which is the word of God. Thereby plainly giving us to underſtand that a chriſtian is ſtill in danger, ready to enter into liſts and to deſcend into the combat.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:31470:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. The conſideration whereof may ſerve in the 1. place to diſcountenance that fond conceit of wicked men: who think it an eaſy matter to be a ſound and faithfull chriſtian. <hi>They lye downe in their beds of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory, they drinke wine in bowles, they eat of the lambs of the flock and the calves of the ſtall</hi> (as the ſcripture ſpeaks) they ſuffer themſelves to be lull'd in the lap, and muzzled in the boſome of all carnall delights, without any ſtriving or ſtrugling againſt theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemies of God and goodneſſe. Nay by ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into uncleanneſſe, and laying of the reines looſe into all manner of prophaneſſe: they give plaine evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence both to God and man, that they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred pay, are reckoned amongſt the ſouldiers, and fight under the banner of ſinne and Satan. And yet notwithſtanding they are as good chriſtians and as ſound profeſſours as the beſt. But alas! alas! theſe men put themſelves into a fooles paradiſe, they are not as they thinke they are, for then they would not be at league with ſinne, but in armes againſt it. Nay on the contrary they rather ſhew themſelves, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come true traytors, to God and to themſelves, who in the midſt of ſuch grand-enemies, (as the fleſh, the <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>devill</hi>) have ſuch peace without contending, ſuch truce without oppoſing ſo quiet and calme a league without all manner of reſiſtance. Marvel not then ye monſters of ſinne though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ye ſee poore chriſtians looke with a ſad coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, or ſorrowfull carriage. It is not an eaſy task to give Satan the foyle: his darts are fiery conſume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31470:9"/>the ſpirits. How is it poſſible on a ſudden to make havocke of a mans naturall corruption? or to deſtroy that life of ſinne which for ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hath had being in our ſoules? Delude not then your ſelves any longer in crying peace, for you ſee chriſtians are fighters. And they that will be warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Chriſts camp, ſhall have dreadfull dreames, fearefull viſions, troubles without, terrors within, and now and then the Arrowes of the Almighty to ſtick into and drink up their ſpirits. Acquaint thy ſelfe with <hi>Iob,</hi> demand of <hi>David</hi> what wounds they received in this warfare, and what it is to be a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſouldier, ſuch can tell thee. Yet if thou wouldſt know by experience, leave off thy wicked aſſociates, change the courſe of thy lewd life, and fight the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer of thy God, and then thou ſhalt finde thy thoughts to bee many; thy heart heavy, thy griefe great and thy feare terrible.</p>
            <p>Uſe. 2. This may ſerve in the ſecond place to comfort the godly who have bickerings with the fleſh, skirmiſhes with the world, and alwayes warre with the devill: yea the very bitterneſſe of aſſaults encountering with them let them not be daunted or diſmay'd; for this is no other thing then that which is incident unto the profeſſion of thoſe that fight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colours of Chriſt. Doth the fleſh entice thee, the world allure thee, the devill tempt thee, yea &amp; his inſtruments moleſt thee. Let this then refreſh thee that it is no other evill then which did befall the deareſt of Gods children. The caſe is common
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31470:9"/>with them. For when the ſtrong man keeps the houſe all is at peace at home, but goe about to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe him then will hee rage and teare. If <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> begins to repayre the walls of <hi>Ieruſalem, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballet</hi> ſhall oppoſe him; <hi>Paul</hi> to preach the Goſpell, his owne countrey-men will perſecute him. Satan when his kingdom ſhakes will rouze up himſelf, arm all his Agents to act their parts leaſt <hi>Babell</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and overturned. Let not theſe things ſeem ſtrange to thee, for no combat, no chriſtian. When the devill doth aſſault thee, the body of corruption lyes heavy upon thee, and death with his many Ghoſtly forms terrifies thee, then conclude thou either art or ſhalt be a right reſolute heavenly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour: For theſe are foes to all them that fight for the Lord or the land of life.</p>
            <p>Uſe. 3. Seeing that faithfull men are military men; let us then in the laſt place labour to ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our guard: like traine-ſouldiers let our armour be alwayes in readines; for the place wherein we are (which is the Church) is militant, our calling Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, not one minute can pleade a priviledge fom an encounter. If the caſe were thus with our bodies that we were ſtill in danger to be ſet upon by our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and knew not when he would fall upon us we would bee carefull to bee well provided. Thus is it with our ſoules; and therefore by how much the more excellent the one is then the other, &amp; by how much the more puiſſant and powerfull the ſpirituall enemy is then the corporal, by ſo much the higher it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31470:10"/>concerne us to ſtand upon our guard. Now that wee may quit ourſelves like heavenly warriours; let us have theſe fowre weapons alwayes in readineſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt knowledge; this is like unto <hi>Sampſons</hi> eyes who for the want of them could not find the pillars of the houſe: no more can we the principles of faith unleſſe knowledge guide us. For without this weele oft foyle our friends, when wee ſhould wound our foes, and range beyond our rankes, when we ſhould keep within our files. Thus it was with <hi>Paul</hi> before he did receive Chriſts preſſe-mony, through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he made havock of the Church of God, and <hi>Peter</hi> on the ſame ground did promiſe what he was not able to performe. Without knowledge the mind is not good, and blind men are not fit to fight, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept under the Prince of darkneſſe, and therefore we muſt labour in the firſt place to bee arm'd with knowledge.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Courage, what heroicall ſpirit hath that man need to have who is to wraſtle with principalities and powers, with an heavy burden of ſinne and ſtrong body of corruption, he had not need to be a puleing babe, affrighted with the power of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. But as litle <hi>David</hi> was not diſmay'd ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the threats of his enemy that great Giant at <hi>Gath,</hi> or the greatneſſe of his lookes, or the ſtrength of his hands, but did with the greateſt valour over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, ſo muſt we doe, arme our ſelves againſt Satans forces not flying back when he ſeeks to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault us, but meet him moſt ſtoutly, oppoſing coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31470:10"/>both his power and policy, untill we have wonne the victory, who otherwiſe would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayled had we not been armed with courage.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Love; This weapon will ſtirre up our ſpirits, and adde life unto all our actions, when wee our ſelves grow feeble and weake; the Apoſtle tells us it is of a laſting nature, that when all other weapons fayle, yet this will endure. Let Satan be enraged ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much againſt us, and raiſe up his inſtruments to moleſt and hurt us; yet love will make us ſtand to our ground, reſiſt unto blood. And though death it ſelfe ſuppriſe us as the ſtrongeſt dart, yet love to our captaine the Lord Ieſus hath taken away her ſting, ſo that our enemies cannot mortally wound us: they may only bruiſe us in the heele they ſhall never breake our heads, nor give us a deadly ſtroke.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Power; The Prophet <hi>David</hi> being an old ſouldier prayes for it. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.2. <hi>S. Paul</hi> a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy warriour often commends it. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. A chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould bee like that <hi>Leviathan Iob</hi> ſpeakes of,
<note place="margin">Iob. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> his heart firme as ſtone, his bones as braſſe, hee accounts Iron as ſtraw, and eſteemeth ſteele as ſtubble, no arrow can make him flee, nor ſpeare turne him from the battayle. Want of power makes us a prey to our enemies: and then wee are moſt in danger to looſe the field when wee are not able to fight; Let us be armed therefore with power. Hee that hath knowledge without power is like a ſouldier that hath his eyes but wants his armes. He that hath knowledge, and power, is like a ſouldier that hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31470:11"/>his eyes and armes but without courage wants his heart. He that hath knowledge, power, and courage, is like a ſouldier, that hath his eyes, his armes, his heart; yet without love he lacks his lims. For power can warre, but without courage dares not; power, courage can, and dare, but without love will not; power, courage, love, can, dare, and will, yet if know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge direct not, there will be no good event in the combat. Wherefore get knowledge that will direct thee, get courage that will embolden thee, get love that will conſtraine thee, get power that will enable thee. For he that wants any of theſe ſhall never bee crowned, except with ſhame and endleſſe confuſion. Arme then thy ſelfe with theſe be valiant till thou beeſt victorious, ſo that in the concluſion of thy dayes thou mayſt confeſſe here with <hi>S. Paul I have fought a good fight</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with mans Military conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein you have ſeen how hee becomes a figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I am now to ſpeake of the laſt act or part which he playes on the ſtage of this world. The finiſhing of his courſe. Hence I collected that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. As his condition is military ſo is it mortall.</p>
            <p>God puts an end to all his encounters; ſo that his life is nothing elſe but a marching to death. As ſoon as wee be borne wee begin to draw to an end, as if the whole ſcope of our deſires were to haſten to the grave. The cleareſt day is covered by the clouds of the night, the longeſt ſentence muſt have it's period,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31470:11"/>and there is no life on earth but hath it's death. As if death were the marke which the vanity of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane endeavours runs at. All men, yea all inferiour things are freed by an end. And as the Philoſopher anſwered the newes of his ſons death; <hi>Scio me ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuiſſe mortalem,</hi> I have gotten a man that is mortall. So God the Father may ſay of every man living, <hi>Scio me creâſse mortalem.</hi> I have made man that hath made himſelfe mortall.
<note place="margin">Per nativita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vivet in carne, per ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventutem candeſcit in flore, per mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aret in pulvere. Greg.</note> Hence is that ſaying of an ancient ſetting forth mans frayle eſtate, <hi>By birth a man is borne greene in his fleſh, by youth he is white in his bloſsome, by death hee is withered in the duſt.</hi> It is a law enacted by the king of heaven; <hi>Statutum eſt omnibus ſemelmori.</hi> It is appointed for all once to dye. It is appointed, and that by him whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees are like thoſe of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> which cannot be altered. Death like the fiſher-man enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all kinde of fiſh in his net, old and young, good and bad, ſmall and great. All is catch'd by death. Which thing the Poets inſinuate in the fable of <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Cupid</hi> who lodging at a time both in one Inne enterchanged each others arrowes, and ſo from that time to this it comes to paſſe that old men dote and yong men dye. If they that have brought us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world are gone out of it before us, wee may conclude our own following. There is not one in the whole cluſter of man-kinde but <hi>eodem modo &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do vinctus &amp; victus,</hi> is lyable to the common and equall law of death. Mans body ſo well as Ice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds that ridle. The mother begets the daughter.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31470:12"/>Duſt begets the body,
<note place="margin">Gignit filia matrem.</note> and the body begets duſt. Our life is like a game at cheſſe wherein men ſupply different places, one is a king, another a Queene, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother a Biſhop, another a Knight, another a pawn, but when the game is ended, and they ſhuffled into one bagge all is alike. So death makes no diſtinction betwixt Prince and people, Soveraign and ſubjects, the robes of the one ſo well as the ragges of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall not eſcape her ruine. When <hi>Alcibiades</hi> brags of his lands <hi>Socrates</hi> reaches him a Map, bids him demonſtrate where they lye. Alas he could not find, nor ſcarce diſcerne <hi>Athens</hi> it ſelfe, it was ſo ſmall a point in reſpect of the world.
<note place="margin">Ecce vix to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Hercules implerit ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note> The duſt of mighty <hi>Hercules</hi> can ſcarce fill a pitcher. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſaid of <hi>Alexander,</hi> yeſterday the world did not content him, now ten cubits can containe him. It's worthy our conſideration that had we as much land as ever the devill ſhewed Chriſt, yet wee can call no more ours but the grave. This is the eſtate of the beſt that when they have devoured the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate creatures, the wormes ſhall devoure them. A fat corps is but a fat ſupper for the wormes. It is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther birth nor bravery, riches nor royalty, that can ſtop us from finiſhing of our courſe or runing of our race untill all be concluded by death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Seeing wee are mortall, let this then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us to reflect upon our ſelves. It is the folly of miſerable man to be too much unmindful of the day of death. And indeed the faſhion of ſecure wretches when they have been forgetfull of any thing to ſay
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31470:12"/>they thought no more of it then of the day of their death. Intimating hereby however they think of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, yet the thoughts of death are farre from them. Theſe are not apprehenſive of their common condition, hence unawares they are ſupprized and ſent packing to hell in the midſt of their wretched ſecurity. Oh conſider this you that are unmindfull of your end, putting far from you the evill day the time of your diſſolution. Remember that as the tree falls ſo it lyes, as death leaves thee ſo ſhall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment finde thee. As thou ſoweſt here ſo thou muſt reap hereafter. If thou haſt been a ſwearer, a curſer, a prophane wretch; look for ſuch a crop as this ſeed will bring forth, which without repentance is no leſſe then everlaſting horrour with devills and damned ſpirits in a lake that burnes with fire and brimſtone. Bee then counſelled forthwith to bee mindfull of thy end. And for thy better proceeding conſider theſe motives.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The uncertainty of it;
<note place="margin">Nil certius morte, horâ mortis nihil incertius.</note> we ſee by dayly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience though ſtrong bodies may perhaps hold out many fits unexpectedly they are forced to yeild to the neceſſity of nature. Our bodies are made of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, weak and fluid principles; and therefore ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner reſolve to their firſt materialls. Doe we not ſee that though ſome bee ſuffered like ripe fruit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine on the tree till the fall, to live till they be old; yet how many be cudgeld fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tree, ſnatcht away by death in the very prime of their dayes. Was not <hi>Herod</hi> wounded deadly in the midſt of his pomp
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31470:13"/>and pride by this meſſenger. Surely had hee then been a painting of himſelfe as many of our Ladyes doe, death would ſoon have ſpoyled all his colours. How ſoone did that covetous muck worme in the Goſpell?
<note place="margin">Luke 12, 10.</note> that thought by his wealth to purchaſe heaven on earth, heare that ſad knell ringing in his eares; <hi>this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee.</hi> His day of pleaſure is ended, and the night of everlaſting ſorrow ſupprizes him.
<note place="margin">Extremum gau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ij luctus occupat.</note> Vexation treads on the heels of vanity. That when pleaſure like the ſunne hath run her courſe ſhe ſets (unawares) oft-times in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall night of paine. Let the uncertainty therefore of our ends cauſe us to bee prepared for them. Wee know not how ſoon the great Iudge will appeare in the cloudes to call us to a reckoning, let us take heed of being found wrapt in a cloud of dark ignorance and blind ſecurity. Wee muſt know that cloud will diſſolve ours, and lay us open with our ſinnes to the view of men and Angells. Let us be carefull to make all now even with God. And as <hi>Alcibiades</hi> told <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> when hee was troubled with ſtudying how to give his accounts, that if he would be ruled by him he ſhould rather ſtudy how to give no account at all. So ſay I, let thy whole endeavour be now employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in advancing the honour of thy God, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after he cannot call thee to an account, becauſe here thou haſt his acquaintance given thee which will fully ſatisfy his demands hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. The hazzard and danger we are lyable unto in being unmindfull of death; Which is no leſſe then
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31470:13"/>to be tumbled into eternity of torment,
<note place="margin">A quolibet monento pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det aeternitas.</note> with devills and damned reprobates. For upon every moment of time depends eternity, either our everlaſting woe, or everlaſting welfare; and if wee ſhould bee ſwept away before we thought on our ends, what horrour and vengeance would ſupprize us. Yea wee ſhould then undergoe both the puniſhment of loſſe, and ſenſe, and bee baniſhed from the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our gracious God, and caſt into unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire; there to feele nothing but continuall cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty exerciſed both againſt body and ſoule, by malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous devills without the ſmalleſt intermiſſion or eaſe. As therefore we tender the good of our ſoules, ſo let the danger we are lyable to by being unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of our mortality prevayle with us to prepare for our latter end.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. The happines we ſhall enjoy in being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of our mortality; we ſhall hereby become to bee placed in the higheſt honour, even to ſet with Kings and Princes, to live in the largeſt kingdome, even the kingdome of heaven, to inherit the durableſt riches where neither moth nor ruſt can corrupt nor theeves breake thorow nor ſteale. when once wee arrive here wee ſhall hunger no more, nor thirſt no more; neither griefe nor ſorrow ſhall poſſeſſe our ſoules, but all teares ſhall be wiped from our eyes, all feares taken from our hearts; and nothing but joy and peace, but love and goodneſſe ſhall encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe us, and that not for a day, or an houre, or an yeare, but for eternity. The ſenſe of this happineſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31470:14"/>ſhall never have an end. But after that we have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed our courſe and kept the faith, we ſhall be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with righteouſneſſe which is the ample reward of our holy endeavours. And brings me now briefly to the laſt concluſion namely</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. That if we ſight couragiouſly our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſhall not be fruſtrated. God will give vs <hi>a crowne of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſervices of men it oft-times falls out that many for the good endeavours and carefull em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in their maſters buſineſſes are ſo farre from being rewarded according to their demerits as that they are not regarded by them. They fiſh faire but in the end catch nothing worth accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; they have their labour for their paines. But it is not thus in the ſervice of God, he is ſo far from not regarding his ſervants as that he doth moſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally extend his hands of bounty towards them farre beyond, ſhall I ſay their deſerts? (I know they have none at all; their well-doings extend not to him,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes, doe what they can, they are unprofitable ſervants) but farre beyond their deſires, for ſuch things which neither eye hath ſeen, nor eare heard, neither can it enter into mans heart to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what God hath prepared for them that feare him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which point is both pregnantly and clearely proved in ſcripture. <hi>The tree of life</hi> which is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God is promiſed to <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> To eat <hi>the Mannah that is hid,</hi> and <hi>a white ſtone,</hi> and in that white ſtone <hi>a new name written in it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31470:14"/>which no man knoweth ſave him that receiveth it,</hi> is promiſed to <hi>Pergamus. Power over nations</hi> is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dto <hi>Thyatira. while Arras</hi> is promiſed to <hi>Sardis,</hi> to be <hi>a pillar in the Temple of God</hi> is promiſed to <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia</hi> if they remaine conſtant in their profeſſion. And if <hi>Smirna</hi> be faithfull unto death ſhee ſhall bee ſure to have a crowne of life. As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah's</hi> dreames, both <hi>Pharoah's</hi> dreames are one. So it may be ſaid of theſe promiſes they are one, point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out unto us one and the ſame thing, the ample and gracious goodneſſe of God both in reſpecting and rewarding the painfull labours of his children. A paralell hereof is that of <hi>Solomon Prov.</hi> 11.18. <hi>The wicked works a deceitfull work, but to him that ſoweth righteouſneſse ſhall be a ſure reward.</hi> Hence this came to bee a concluded point and out of queſtion in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> divinity. That when the ſunne of his life was at the point of ſetting, he doth upon conſideration hereof comfort himſelfe in this chapter: yea when hee was ready to bee offered (as he ſpeaks) and the time of his departing drew nigh at hand; This was his Swan-like ſong, <hi>I have fought a good fight I have finiſhed my courſe.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1. This may ſerve in the firſt place to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the faithfull, and courage them in all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, who endeavour to feare the Lord in all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and truth. They may from hence collect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable comfort to themſelves, there is not one prayer they make, not one chapter they read, not one Sermon they heare, but ſets them forward for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31470:15"/>heaven, and enlarges their future happineſſe. What ſhould more comfort them then to enjoy a crowne; to which they being as heires muſt needs tranſport their thoughts beyond all admiration. It is reputed among men no ſmall honour to be called to the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all race any way, either by conſanguinity, or affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Hence is that of <hi>David</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.23. <hi>ſeemeth it to you a light thing to be a Kings ſonne in law.</hi> How much more then ſhould it comfort the faithfull, that they are of a kingly race and a royall kindred. God himſelfe who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, he is their father and they his ſonnes, and ſo are thereby become heires to this crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which S. <hi>Paul</hi> here ſpeaks of. Comfort then your ſelves ye beloved of the Lord, let nothing daunt or diſmay you, neither the forces of the world, nor the frownes of the wicked, the policy of the devill, or the feare of death; but know that if you ſight valiantly and keep the faith, there is comfort enough to recompence all your labours in this <hi>crowne of righteouſneſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Let this then exhort us not to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in well-doing, but with that good woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> cry and continue in crying, be ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, ſeeing your reward is ſo great if yee continue to the end. Be not like him who in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions was wont to ſay the firſt day <hi>Gloria patri,</hi> the ſecond <hi>filio,</hi> the third <hi>ſpiritui ſancto.</hi> Doubling over his Oriſons, and no whit further he was at the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31470:15"/>yeares end then at the beginning; but labour to goe forward in the wayes of obedience. If here you faint your loſſe will prove great, for you looſe no leſſe then <hi>a crown.</hi> Which is not a voluptuous crown of Roſes as wiſdome ſpeakes, nor a crowne of pride to which a woe belongeth, as <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28. Nor ſuch a crowne which is ſet upon the heads of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons and beaſts in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and ſo <hi>Corona vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſa ruinoſa</hi> as one ſpeaks, nor yet as the <hi>Poets</hi> crownes of Lawrell and Ivy litle better then weeds which wrapt about <hi>Ionah's</hi> head, traſh of no valew. And as our Saviour ſaid that his kingdom was not of this world, ſo theſe crownes are none of his crowns, but a crowne where death hath no claime, a crowne where danger is not incident, a crowne not encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with croſſes, but a crowne enriched with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting comforts. O labour then to fight valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it, be not faint-hearted.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Gideons</hi> army all faint-hearted ſouldiers were commanded to ſtay at home. No cowards ſhall ever obtaine this crowne. It is a ſtrange thing to conſider how inconſtant chriſtians are in ſeeking this <hi>crowne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſome are of many minds, many moods, now forward, then backward, full of moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and commotions, ebbing and flowing like <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> ſeaven times a day. Some are neither forward nor backward neither ebbe nor flow like <hi>Mare mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> but are betwixt the religious and irreligious juſt ſtanding water. But theſe like cowards goe back, fall off in the day of battaile. I meane at the day of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31470:16"/>death when Satan doth double his forces. As the king of <hi>Aſsyria</hi> charged his captaines to <hi>fight neither with ſmall nor great ſave only with the King of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings. 22.</note> So the Prince of darkneſſe commands the leader of his troupes, and thoſe that ſtand at the head of his company, his maſter-temptations not ſo fight againſt any vertue ſmall or great; but continuance in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>quam ſolùm novit coronari.</hi> Vpon whoſe head he knowes the crowne muſt fall. Then hee beſtirres himſelfe not only becauſe he knowes his owne time is but ſhort: but becauſe he perceives ours to bee ſo. Therefore he doubles his forcſs as if he ſtill meanes to make the laſt conflict the ſoreſt, reſolving to ſet all at the ſtake and either now to winne or ſit downe with loſſe and deſpaire. Oh how ſhould we now la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour then to procure a true faith; and having got it to keep it: that ſo our common enemy may not beat off our conſtancy in fighting under his colours who in the end will ſurely crowne us. We know eternall life is not given to all, for then we would all preſume; nor to none, for then wee would deſpaire. But <hi>vincenti dabitur, to him that overcometh, he that fighteth the good fight of faith,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did in the text: and as our gracious ſiſter this renowned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman hath done: whom you now ſee to have <hi>finiſhed her courſe,</hi> and whom as hereafter I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare hath <hi>kept the faith.</hi> Let this then teach thee to be valiant unto the laſt minute. The eye of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Lord Ieſus is upon thee if thou faint to cheare thee, if thou fight to ſecond thee, if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31470:16"/>to crowne the, as he did S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the text who being confident of the ſame did thus conclude with himſelfe, <hi>I haue fought &amp;c.</hi> And ſo I am come from the text to the occaſion.</p>
            <p>The death of man in generall is able to make our ſorrowes runne, what pitty is it, that hee that even now was <hi>Monarch</hi> of the ayre, to breath where he liſted, ſhould ſuddenly have his lungs ſtopt with duſt, and bee lockt up well-nigh for ever in the breathleſſe earth. That he that kept the beſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany with men, ſhould forthwith have no better compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then wormes. Certainly if wee could blow up this powder into our heads it might awake our ſouls from ſleeping in ſecurity; eſpecially if we take up this conſideration withall; that the ſame death that ſlew our worthy ſiſter here may next tread upon our own heeles.</p>
            <p>But above all things me thinks this ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayle moſt with us, the death of the faithfull Saints of God. Which as it is precious in Gods eyes ſo the more pittyfull for us to behold. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breakes ranck and dyes there falls <hi>a vapour,</hi> but when a godly perſon dyes there falls <hi>a ſtare.</hi> When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhook of <hi>Aegypt</hi> and departed, they rob'd the <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> and when a good perſon ſhakes of the world ſhe robbes the world. Such was the death of this thrice worthy and ever renowned gentlewoman, whom death too ſoone for us, though too late for her ſelfe hath with an <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> removed into another world. I know it is an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31470:17"/>uſuall cuſtome upon ſuch ſolemne occafions as this, to receive the worth of ſuch perſons as wee know both in life and death to bee truly commendable. And to warrant our actions, wee have Gods word to ſecond us; who as he would have the name of the wicked to rot, ſo he would have that the memoriall of the righteous ſhould remaine for ever. On which ground I am the more bold to blaze her worth, the commemoration whereof as it is profitable to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, ſo is it likewiſe acceptable and pleaſing to God, who in the fame of his <hi>Saints</hi> is chiefly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured as the ſole Author of every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect guift.
<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1.17.</note> Their lives are as lines by which we may leade our owne.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polyb. hiſt. lib.</hi> 1.</note> And as <hi>Polybius</hi> wiſely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth; there is not a more expedite way to inſtruct us and to ſtir us up unto a good life, then by obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſincere piety of faithfull perſons whom the Almighty hath been pleaſed to gather to himſelfe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vt qui prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendimur ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem exemplis incitemur. Greg Mor. l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> We are not eaſily moved by precepts, examples are more prevalent, practiſe having proved that facile in performance, which to our ſluggiſh diſpoſitions, by precept only, ſeemed very difficult. therefore,</p>
            <p>That God may have praiſe and we reap the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of an excellent patterne, I ſhall adventure as well as I can to ſhew forth Her honour whom I know to be every way truly honourable. But before I make my words good, let your beliefe goe along with me to remove all prejudiciall conceits. For I doe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely confeſſe, I ſhall not out of privat affection pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the truth. For though Her memory be deare
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31470:17"/>to me (as the reliques of our loving friend are wont to be,) yet truth muſt ſtill be dearer,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.6.</note> and <hi>love it ſelfe rejoyceth in the truth.</hi> Let others if they pleaſe imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate bad lawyers, who for their fees will plead and commend any cauſe. For my owne part, my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not of ſo large a ſize, neither will I extend it further then her worth and goodneſſe ſhall bind me.</p>
            <p>We will beginne therefore in the firſt place from whence ſhe took her beginning, at her birth and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree. She was cut out of no meane quarry. It was a cuſtome amongſt the <hi>Indians,</hi> ſayes <hi>Phyloſtratus,</hi> after the death of any worthy perſon to inſcribe his acts upon the dores of his houſe for the ennobling of his iſſue. So it was ever eſteemd no meane bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be well deſcended. And ſurely if I ſhould take upon me here the part of an <hi>Herald,</hi> &amp; in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them write upon the doors of her houſe her deſcent both by father and mother, I could eaſily derive her (as you know better then my felfe) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from Honourable, Right Honourable, and truly noble blood. But what is greatneſſe without grace, or honour without goodneſſe, but as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banet which wants the Iewell; or the Casket that is empty of gold. It is the greateſt infamy to bee like unto hills, the higher the barrener; when wee ſhould be as Diamonds, the bigger, the better. But ſuch was not this vertuous gentlewoman I may ſay of her truly in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>ſhe was fruitfull in good works.</hi> Theſe ſhined in her devout ſoule like heaps of Diamonds in rings of gold: being the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31470:18"/>of true nobility did declare to the world her deſcent from the royalleſt blood, the great King of heaven. It is Godlines that makes us truly great, and though wee bee never ſo much honoured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men on earth, yet if we be not Gods favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites we dye in infamy, and our very names ſhall rot. But enough of her birth which wee all know was honourable.</p>
            <p>Let us come in the next place to her life, ſhee had (as we all now have) A courſe to finiſh, but this is her happineſſe, her journey is at an end, our miſery, we are ſtill a travailing towards it. Shee hath that in fruition which we only yet hope for, even this <hi>crown of righteouſneſſe</hi> in the text. Now if the world en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how ſhe hath got it, or the way ſhe took to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. I anſwer in the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> by <hi>fighting a good fight and keeping the faith.</hi> She was a right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant heavenly warriour, that at the concluſion of her dayes, not three houres before that laſt one of her death, I found her to have her weapons in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Knowledge, Courage, Love,</hi> and <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Knowledge,</hi> which by continuall practiſe from dayly reading of the word ſhe had procured. Shee did not like <hi>Martha<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> encomber her ſelfe with wordly buſineſſe, but with <hi>Mary,</hi> did chuſe the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part. And this did her dayly practiſe declare, whoſe conſtant courſe was foure times in the day to ſet her ſelfe a part for the ſervice of her God. So that I may ſay of her, as it is ſpoken of devout S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> ſhe lived every day as her laſt day. And thus labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31470:18"/>to encreaſe in knowledge ſhe did attain to no ſmall meaſure of it; for a litle before her death when I began to tell her of Satans wiles to beat us off from being confident of Gods favour when wee were in the weakeſt ſtate to reſiſt him: with much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhe returnes me anſwer in that comfortable expreſſion of S. <hi>Pauls, Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>I am perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angells,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.39</note> 
               <hi>nor principalities nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall bee able to ſeparate me from the love of God which is in Christ Jeſus our Lord.</hi> Thus word for word as ſtrong as ſhe was able a litle before her diſſolution expreſt her ſelfe. Neither was this perſwaſion grounded on a generall knowledge which is a common guift, but on a practicall, experimentall, and ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which none are enricht with but ſuch for whom God hath layed up <hi>a crown of righteouſneſse.</hi> There are indeed a generation of men and women that pretend much knowledge, but in her it was reall, not in pretence. Shee was none of thoſe talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ladies,</hi> whoſe Religion appeares onely in the tongue. But ſhee was more for good works then words. Much like unto that worthy woman the mother of S. <hi>Greg: Nazianzen</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that had ſhee an Ocean of wealth ſhee would have emptyed it all into the bellies of the poore. So I may ſay of this vertuous Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there was an Ocean of pitty encloſed within the compaſſe of her heart, and when any poore neighbour ſtood in need
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31470:19"/>of her bounty, ſhe gave moſt liberally to them. And all this did ariſe from her knowledge, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſmalleſt releife given to the diſtreſſed members of Chriſt, ſhould not paſſe unrewarded at the laſt day.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. As ſhee did abound in <hi>knowledge,</hi> ſo with <hi>Courage,</hi> for though death, which to nature and ſenſe is ſaid to bee the moſt terrible of terribles, yet the thought of it did not any way daunt her ſpirits. She could with boldneſſe looke death in the face, which when ſhe was put in mind of the approaching hour, thus heavenly expreſt her ſelfe, that <hi>howſoever God was pleaſed to diſpoſe of her, whether for life or death, like a couragious chriſtian ſhe concluded ſhee ſhould bee the Lords.</hi> Reſolving like <hi>Iob</hi> to undergoe affliction patiently, and with S. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſuffer death willingly, if the Lord be ſo pleaſed or hath appointed it. Now would you know the reaſon of this courage? It was that holy practiſe of her life: whereby continuall purging and embracing all gracious opportunities of hearing the word preached, ſhee did ſo dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new her covenant with her God, as that hereby the ſting of death being taken away it could not any way affright her. A rare patterne for the greateſt Ladyes to follow, whoſe life if they did but ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider, would confine themſelves more unto their cloſets to meditate on God and goodneſſe, then now they looſe time in their chambers, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving of faſhions and following the vanities of this ſinfull world. Oh remember you great ones of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31470:19"/>world, that you are but duſt, and you know not how ſoone you may bee reſolv'd to your firſt principle which is duſt. Now if in the midſt of your worldly pomp and honour you ſhould ſee death appeare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly, as <hi>Belthazar's</hi> hand-writing did on the wall, before you had made your peace with your God, how would it make your joynts to tremble; how would it fill you with horror and amazement? eſpecially to thinke that you have ſerved no other God but your pleaſures, you never ſought after that which would have made you truly honourable. Surely if theſe ſerious thoughts could but poſſeſſe your ſoules with this vertuous Gentlewoman, you would turn your times of playing into praying; and by making the word of God your delight, would endeavour (with this now glorious Saint,) to procure the aſſurance which at the finiſhing of your courſe would make you <hi>more then Conquerors through the Lord Ieſus Christ that loved us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. She was armed with <hi>Love;</hi> in reſpect of which vertue I may ſay of her, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of the good woman <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.2. <hi>Many daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou ſurpaſseſt them all.</hi> Her good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this particular was in the ſuperlative degree before many others of her quality; which will am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply appeare in the ſeverall ſtreams of affection which flowed from that fountaine of love in her heart. For firſt if you will view it as it appeared towards her her husband, and ſo you ſhall find it ſtreame forth in abundance. Being as moſt reall ſo moſt diſcreet,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31470:20"/>hence in the whole courſe of their lives, ſo long as they lived together, they ſo loved that the ſmalleſt diſcontent was not found to prejudice each others affection. A rare preſident for moſt married wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who through their indiſcretion it oftentimes falls out that ſmall jarres break forth into great quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells, yea I had almoſt ſaid to the ſeparation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugall affection. Let ſuch remember here is a wife worthy their imitation, who by the ſweetneſſe of her diſpoſition, the amiableneſſe of her perſon, the meakneſſe of her behaviour, the reſplendant vertues that ſhe was adorned with, did ſo comply with her husbands diſpoſition, that ſhee may ſhine as a rare patterne to light others in the like way to practiſe. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. if you will view her <hi>Love</hi> as it ſtreamed forth towards Gods miniſters: and here it appeared very great. For of Her, herein I may truly ſay with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhe did <hi>highly eſteem of them for their works ſake.</hi> She was none of thoſe proud Ladyes, that love to ſee Gods Miniſters ſtand at a diſtance from them; leaſt they melt the paint of their faces with the heat of reproofe. But ſo meek and humble was ſhe, and ſo willing to give care to heavenly inſtructions, that now ſhe reaps the fruits of thoſe coeleſtiall comforts which are conveighed unto the ſoule by the word of grace. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. If you view Her <hi>Love</hi> as it ran forth to releive the members of Ieſus Chriſt it here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares great alſo. She was in this particular like ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dorcas</hi> towards them, full of good works, feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only their bellies, but alſo cloathing their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31470:20"/>backs, releiving them bountifully, maintaining them liberally. So that by Her love they were enabled to live of themſelves, who before were not able to maintaine their owne charge. So abounding in good works was this woman, that though Her death be Her owne greateſt gaine, yet to many objects of pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will prove the greateſt loſſe. Laſtly. I may not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that ſtreame of <hi>Love,</hi> which did moſt nobly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the neceſſity of Her old ſervants. It's a thing litle thought upon by many great perſons, who out of conſcience ſhould conſider, and provide for their old and faithfull ſervants. Wee may not wonder to ſee young ſerving-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to become old beggars; when they meet with ſuch unconſcionable maſters, who often-times inſtead of rewarding them will take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to caſhiere them; and well may they then beg, who are not able to worke for themſelves. But this vertuous perſon was never of this temper, but as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſo eſpecially at Her death did liberally provide for them. And gave them ſeverall Legacies to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their ſtock they had gotten in Her ſervice. Who as herein they ſhall have cauſe to remember Her <hi>Love,</hi> ſo eſpecially Gods goodneſſe in placing them under ſo gracious a Miſtris. Thus you ſee what an Ocea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Love</hi> poſſeſt this vertuous foule. And as ſhe was arm'd with <hi>Love,</hi> ſo in the laſt place with <hi>Power.</hi> God being infinitely gracious to her, in enabling Her to reſiſt, yea overcome the enimies of Her ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Trampling the world underfoot, as unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or give any thoughts thereof the ſmalleſt entertainement.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:31470:21"/>
            <p> Her affections were placed according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſoule, onely on things above. Though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might labour to tempt and move Her to diſtruſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoughts, yet all was in vaine. For God had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> enricht Her ſoule with the aſſurance of his favor that the gates of Hell could not prevaile agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Her, ſo infinitely filled was Her divine ſoule w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> heavenly raviſhments, that whiles ſhee was al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſpeak, uttered nothing but coeleſtiall ejaculation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and when ſhe was deprived of that benefit, lifted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Her hands, which were the Indexes of Her con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> praying; and thus having fought a good fight, and finiſhed her courſe, kept the faith, ſhe is now an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tainer of that <hi>Crowne of righteouſneſse</hi> which S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> here ſpeaks of, which crowne the Lord of his in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite mercy give us for his ſonne our Saviour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt his ſake, by whom alone wee are more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Conquerours. And to whom with the Father and the Eternall ſpirit; Three perſons, one immort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and everlivng God, be aſcribed as is moſt due, all honour, and glory, power, praiſe, might, majeſty, and dominion, now and for evermore AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
